I thought you could maybe say something
more about Jonah
I've got some a section of modular 39
so it's part of the the gradual so it's
after the hindrances after having
abandoned these five hindrances
deferments at the mind that we can
understanding quite secluded from sense
desires secluded from unwholesome things
with thinking with pondering he dwells
having attained the first job a joy and
pleasure born of seclusion
he drenches steeps films pervades this
very body with the joy and pleasure born
of seclusion so that there isn't any
part of the entire body that is
unpervaded by the joy and pleasure form
of seclusion imagine bhikkhus a skilled
barber or a barber's apprentice who
having scattered soak powder onto a dish
would sprinkle a bit by bit with water
so that this lump of soap powder goes
moist he comes moist inside there bathed
with moisture and not dripping in just
this way the goose crunches see that's
another thing that people often look
pedido over that message I'm thinking
almost when I get John I get the
pleasure of jhana and then I focus on
their pleasure and I and I sort of
pervade my body with that pleasure but
even even those even those passages says
that the pleasure comes from the being
seclusion from our holes it it occurs to
me that Ashley UN you dwell because you
entered it you dwell in jhana because
you entered it yeah accompanied so with
simultaneous pleasure present which is a
reason like direct result of seclusion
John could you say that could you say
that the first jhana is that pleasures
that joy and pleasure from off seclusion
no that's the point John is not that
Jonna is the clarity of the mind that
has surmounted and experienced pleasure
on account of semantics so if anything
that pleasure will come before the John
standing you minding that pleasure could
you recognize it's a wholesome pleasure
pleasure it basically it's a symptom
that pleasure is a good symptom or few
healing from sensuality here and
unwholesome states and the the pressure
of the hindrances but having comfy on
the by understanding I'm sorry but
having come by on having yes so you
understand the extent of it
you understand that the relief that
arises as a result of it and that's how
you tell me bachata which is why John is
oh also men often are kind of given as a
way of fortifying your understanding of
the Dharma clarity of mindfulness that's
what every John is is held by complete
purity of mind collectiveness like in
unshakable in the terrible context yeah
so pervading your body with this
pleasure well first of all you need to
get that pleasure and you don't get it
by attending to Jana and you get it by
understanding the extent of sensuality
in the five hindrances and surmounting
that extent so it's an indirect thing so
to speak you don't get pleasure by
focusing on sensations in the body you
get pleasure by understanding what is
the nature of the hindrances and me
being subjected to it what is the extent
of it what is the necessary basis for
hindrances and maintain the clarity of
that context in your mind you get the
pleasure as a result of the relief by
realizing exactly so then you get to
provide your body with that pleasure
that has a reason on its own not by now
take this pleasure and conveyed it yeah
cuz they'll be like again going back to
taking things up in the same sense we're
taking hindrances up yeah you pervaded
by protecting the same context because
of which this pleasure resulted so
maintaining the clarity of the domain
recollected s and the extent of the body
does being clear about the extent of the
body oh this is happy and is the clear
you become about the extent of the body
head to toe the clearer it gets pervaded
by the pleasure but you're not taking
the pleasure and sort of smearing it all
over yourself well maybe down to my
shell exact now there is no I am doing
this I'm doing that in the jar now
because it's it's set up properly and
then this has this establishment is the
result of it could you say you pervade
the body with this joy and pleasure
pleasure that comes from seclusion
seclusion you pervade the body with that
by becoming clearer and clearer about
the phenomenon of body yes but providing
the body for it to be pervaded by yes by
providing the body the effect that you
provided body by practicing clarity of
the extent of the body and that's why by
the way you will be above the hindrances
because they are entirely within the
body entirely bodily but you not being
developed in regard to the extent of the
body you get affected and pressured and
burden and subjected to these hindrances
that are entirely bodily entirely
boundary the body cannot occur anywhere
else except within the body that's why
you know it can be sleepy but it's not a
set a hindrance but even even when you
like really really tired and sleepy it
can be a hindrance because it really
it's not determined by what's in your
body in a sense of at its sleep you're
excited something easy tell me how much
the mind is above it or not
so you pervade this body by pleasure the
pleasure has a reason and its own as a
result of withdrawal so now you won't
pervade the body by discerning the body
even more yes for what it is and then
the same pressure will keep a rise in to
that extent
so you that's why not too much not too
little because you can only discern the
extent of the body to the extent that it
is so not this turning extent of the
body correctly means either overdoing it
or underdoing making it too wet or too
dry
so you've overcome the hindrances by
being clear about the bases full
hindrances yes but not being clear in a
sense of figure it out
mnemonics seed isn't necessarily your
present thing right here right now
whether you care before the peripheral
notion of recognition of your body here
enduring as a necessary basis for
excitement for your will for drowsiness
will worry for doubt people who think
doubt is mental it is when it's a
hindrance otherwise it's just like why
would you live literally perceive it as
a kind of bodily discomfort when you're
in in doubt it's all suppose it's on the
level of the auto domain of the other
senses and the body cuz doubt can only
be about the contact thing cannot be
about the nature and content of things
it's already within the layer of the
body you basically without you're always
looking for something with something
past the senses some other thing in the
world so having abandon the five hindrances
so having abandon the five hindrances
having abandoned desire towards the
world any concern regarding the world so
having discerned the body to the
necessary extent as a basis for the
entire world my world a world anything
in between he has to be within the basis
of this product
and now you just maintain that context
when the clarity of your seclusion
becomes developed you will experience
relief because you will feel safe
because you're very funny factual safety
from concern from sensuality from the
hindrances but even then as I said you don't you
but even then as I said you don't you
can't take that pleasure because you
haven't created it so you pervade your
body how well by the same manner you
have provided in the first place by
providing the clarity of the extent
pleasure effects it yeah so you provide
it by fully clarifying that extent
further and for all simply by repeating
it
you will keep pervading it and by the
way is the same like in the in the third
or the fourth jhana I think it's the
fortune I describe there's a covered
with a white cloth yeah yeah like to the
lance basically from the highest tip of
your head to the toe it is not a bit of
the body that's not covered that
something else is included or the body
hasn't been included enough so that's
like when you outline the extent of the
body as a clear context in your mind to
such clarity and refinement such as
imagine if you completely wrapped in a
white cloth just to the extent with your
outlines of your body up and that's how
that pleasure is felt that hence the
simile URI No No
[Music]
yeah thought we'd go through to the
similes didn't the other journalism
similar yeah it could be tomorrow so
when the furthermore bhikkhus with the
calming of thinking and pondering with
internal clarity I must say very
thrilled clarity yeah Chloe give their
context or the extent have a unified
mind so with a unified mind without
thinking without pondering the big who
dwells having attained the second job
enjoy and pleasure born of composure so
now it's not a joy and pleasure
seclusion to pop Samadhi and again he
drenches steeps fills pervades this very
body with the joy and pleasure born of
composure so that there isn't any path
like this pump evaded composure imagine
a lake of spring water for which there
were no inflow from the east from the
west from the north from the south and
the skyward from time to time replenish
it then a cold stream of water having
welled up in the lake the drenched steep
fill pervade that lake with cool water
so there isn't any part of the lake
there isn't something to the extent the
lake is to that extent it's filled with
water
so I told me because you're not doing it
on your own terms you're not feeling it
as much as you wanted with as much as
you desire or as much as you think you
should you get it's getting filled to
the extent that you discern that it can
be filled yes yeah so it's like the lake
determines how far that cool waters
again but yeah only by being clear about
only about being clear about what the
body is the extent of your body can you
be clear about this kind of joy doesn't
exactly it's defined by the extent of
the body not but and that's why there is
no craving in jhana it's impossible to
crave for the pleasure of jhana
if you are doing it that is already
rooted in craving now I want it here I
don't want this it's rooted on the level
of preference
and then there's the fading away of the
joy a big who dwells indifferent
recollected and aware so you're saying
you know it's all based on effectiveness
and I was like so much time to recollect
it and still he's becoming more and more
stronger and clearer and yet exactly
more standing art so and so so he dwells
in different recollected where he
experiences a pleasure with the body he
dwells having attained the third channa
which the never ones described is
dwelling with pleasure indifference
Rekha activities because really the body
indifference with her mind
he drenches steeps fills pervades this
very party with the pleasure free from
joy so there isn't any pastor but it's
an undivided by that he says imagine a
pond of lilies all notices some were
born in the water so some lilies and
lotuses that were born in the water have
grown up submerged in the water without
rising out of it so that cool water
trenches steep spills pervades and tips
and roots so that there isn't any part
of the entire legal notice is amplified
with cool water
again just the kind of identity tip to
the route past oh yeah
the body is like the Lord just it's
fully immersed in the water
there is nothing that hasn't been
permeated by there
and then last one having abandoned
pleasure having abandoned pain with the
previous disappearance of happiness and
unhappiness a bhikkhu dwells having
attained fourth jhana needs neither
pleasure nor pain clarified by the
indifference of recollected nurse so now
the body is not a pleasant or unpleasant
it's just a neutral state with
indifference of the compulsion yeah but
that's not it
well nothing spell
to the extent of the body exactly to the
extent to the body
there's nothing neither pleasure nor
displeasure is felt but neither pleasure
nor pain is a feeling yeah but it's not
okay that's what it is
that's why if you know neither pleasure
nor no pleasure it's us what do you know
what not failing is exactly if you don't
know what neither pleasure nor
displeasure is you are affected by it if
you don't know it which means it's about
some pleasantly hmm
yeah even in case you are not on it so
that they discover some super extra
dimension in between the feelings so
they don't feel no it'sit's either
pleasure displeasure or neutral feeling
which is for them old neutral so they
don't feel any of it and because they
know it that's why it's pleasant that's
a good event yeah the fact is nothing
felt that's why it's pleasant so on one
level it's nothing felt on another level
that is pleasure but it's a different
type of learning so for John it's
exactly that like if you were to to
develop before jhana it would be
impossible to not be another hand
because for Johnny is all about random
magical pleasurable attainment you see
the amount of clarity there to the
clarity body the domain of the
hindrances clarity about the extent of
the body clarity about the nature of the
feeling clarity about the unshakable
imperturbable context of mindfulness
we're going to translate it yeah yeah
being a blade equanimity will have to be
the result of being skilled in basically
not feeling or like like but big being
unmoved by hasn't feeling not as a
method of choice but is a measure of
development given if you want to be
moved it would be impossible it's just
impossible
and then yeah that's the simile that you
the why have you brought said the white
yeah so to the extent he says funny says
he's sitting down he's sitting down
having pervaded this very body with a
purified clarified mind so that there
isn't any part of the body who is not
the pervading isn't with a pleasure or
joy or anything no no it's it's
pervading with a purifying clarified
mind imagine because a man was sitting
up having their sink down I've been
coveting himself from the head for the
white glass of the law and Tony parts of
his body unpervaded by the white cloth
in just this way because the bhikkhu is
sitting down having pervaded this very
body with purified clarified mind so
there isn't any part of the body that is
on pervaded by the purified so in that
case you're not anymore
or another it's still the same the
extent of the body gets pervaded by the
clarity of the mind yeah which is now
that perfect equanimity so your
pervading the extent of the body from
the tip of the head to the feet by the
pleasurable equanimity in pleasurable
indifference so to speak that kind of
what has started indirectly so to speak
till when you pull back hindrances you
need to keep like discerning the
background of the necessary basis for
the hindrances and then you get to
approve them well now going back to the
level where the hindrances are that's
now indirect because the mind got so
established upon that peripheral as the
necessary base as they're like really
what's first and that order cannot be
perverted on so that's what mean if
somebody can develop the mind to the
extent of the fourth jhana it's
virtually impossible to not be enough
because there will be nothing left
they will not be included in the clarity
of the right order right context knew
better with mindfulness so any all and
any basis of passion a version and
distraction
but here we are going over to four giant
the same principle and it's useful I
think for people because you know
everybody likes the idea of Johnny's
nothing wrong with that but you won't
understand that the pleasure has nothing
to do with you and if you have a
pleasure of your meditation and if you
can attend to it directly that's not a
pleasure of John it's the pleasure of
some novelty of some sort of release or
whatever you can do it which is once you
start coming down you're gonna have as I
said yeah but the fact that see you you
can relate to it directly means it's not
the result of your withdrawal from
anything you can be relate to directly
so the pleasure of the jannah is first
oh it's a pleasure to Johnny's pleasure
withdrawal so if you have absolute no
idea what seclusion from sensuality and
finances is you can be safe then to
assume that whatever pressure feeling
meditation is not the pleasure you
should be pursuing if it comes find it
because it's fine
but don't think there's anything special
about is about cultivating that yeah
like you it's not even about cultivating
the wholesome pleasure of the Boudreau
he's just using it as a symptom to like
pervade that we drove further and
further and further so actually really
is when I talking about now the party
seems to be like okay yeah well it
always it's like if we withhold a with
the jealousy like that's why it's you
know touching these attainments with the
body develop in your mind in regard to
the extent of the body and it's actually
that's exactly the reason was even an
aria is not a Nogami yet his he is not
developed to the how did this with the
put it his mind is not developed in
regard to a body I think that's why it
said or he hasn't been developed in the
body that's why that's what sensuality
still arises for him
either the two top she hasn't be
developed to do Nagata body hasn't been
developed in about your mind so he still
has work to do if you have been
developed in regard to the extent of
your own but regardless of the occasion
you have basically developed in regard
to the extent of the hindrances which
means you cannot be endured by them
because what they hinder your outside of
enough as in your surmounted by not
surmounting it they're hindering in the
zoo you get him the bonnet some of the
hindrances are also fat or something oh
yeah yeah but that's a different do I
was thinking you're constantly hindered
by something then you end up developing
of you over it and that's when it's a
fetter no doubt okay but you can feel
yourself from factor of that as you
understand the nature doubt but still be
affected by doubt on the body level in
terms of basically feeling craving in
regard to the unpleasant Pleasant
feeling of doubting something that is a
hindrance without but if you've
developed jhana or even that cannot
touch you
yeah that's why IRA Hunt is the
destroyer of the hindrances whether he's
in John oh not those things cannot
hinder him any more because he's mine
has developed evolve even at its lowest
level it's still above even it is least
composed level least recollected level
it's still above the five hindrances
which is exactly what what makes you not
like when these fetters fall off they
can already appear means you can't go
below that
so peripheral awareness of the body is
the starting point of the body that's
enduring while you're talking sitting
being silent eating going to the toilet
image of the body is there easier
starting point well actually not
starting for any sense restraint again
but the image of the body and you're
sort of getting at that via hindrances
for the beginning in a way yeah yeah
everything dude hindrances as well and
then this sort of indirect pleasure that
comes as this sort of as you realize
you're free from that that then becomes
the way yeah well not just you free from
that but you you realize it's a by
establishing buddy collecting the extent
of the body correctly and then
maintaining their collectiveness
you immediately imply or just freedom
from these hindrances but freedom from
the future enhances yeah so the whole
domain possible things that could happen
none of it can apply and that is felt
that's why it's such a tremendous relief
so something you need to like fabricate
you just need to maintain the context
that relieve the relief will have to
come up with so then you can no yes you
can't have a you can have a relief
without the Jonah and you can't have a
journey without a relief but that's not
because it John is the relief Johnnie's
after the relief so you gather it if you
get a pleasure then you still keep doing
the same thing maintaining the same
context until you kind of become
established upon it so to speak well
it's not flimsy but it doesn't go away
as soon as you sort of something pops up
that's why when I say this steady your
mind in this practice stead you're
minding the theme of Jonah so you can do
that you before John and he dwells yeah
once you steady your mind Danny oh
well in that steadied mind of the relief
from everything and also Andrews
concerns about the world and that's what
John is is where you dwell in it the
heretic - speaking living he lives he lives in
- speaking living he lives he lives in
that state and when I say state I mean
that establishment not like some sort of
oblivious oblivion animal
he lives because the Buddha says whether
he walks talks goes to toilet eats he's
in whatever he does is divine because
he's in Jannah
so practicing the recollectionist of the
extent of your body or say mindfulness
of the body the postures regardless of
what hindrance is there so which means
you're not acting out of hindrance and
you're then maintained in the context
despite the pressure of the hindrances
that's how I copy on the hindrances
which means sometimes it will be more
pleasurable sometimes it will be less
depending on how many hindrances you
have a rising how often and that depends
on you really how much you've been
giving into them before but the less you
act out of them the less you give into
them to let you try to get rid of them
the less you try to indulge them the
less they will arise which means then
your pleasure journey will be more and
more agreeable your practice of Johnny
will be more and more agreeable and if
you if you if you are acting out of the
hindrance your basically it's the only
way to act out of hindrance I know
Juliet the only way yang are the
hindrance is to lose the extent of the
body exactly cuz you're stiffening
yourself yes I can controls if you catch
yourself acting other hindrances other
hi next time I won't do it no you will
yes but you want to do is when you catch
yourself acting other hindrance now
include all over there but again in the
extent of the body and that's how next
time you will not act as much at least
the hindrance to this or not it always
remains bound with the body that's fully
understood and he cannot attain to me
even if I want to do
he was only by not understanding that he
cannot pertain to me as into my mind to
me to my point of view to my desires
that's how it pertained to it so develop
yourself in regard to the body and
sensuality cannot pertain to the line